Guide to the Clifford N. Taylor Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Clifford N. Taylor papers
1920-1924
WA MSS S-1321
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.25
(1 box)
The papers consist of Clifford Taylor's business records and printed material. The business records document the Ku Klux Klan in North Dakota and the American Krusaders and printed material contains publications by the Klan.
Taylor, Clifford N.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 1982.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Clifford N. Taylor Papers consist of one box of correspondence, printed material, and reports relating to Clifford N. Taylor, a Ku Klux Klan "Kleagle" in Devils Lake, North Dakota. The material dates between the years 1920 through 1924, with the majority of the papers spanning the months June through September 1924.
The Knights of the Ku Klux Klan were initially formed in 1867 in Pulaski, Tennessee, but had fallen into decline by the early twentieth century. In 1915, however, the Klan was revitalised and reorganized. The states were divided into nine domains headed by nine Grand Goblins. Each state was headed by a King Kleagle overseeing a corps of local Kleagles. The King Kleagle and the local Kleagles answered to an Imperial Kleagle, who also acted as Chief Treasurer. The local Kleagles functioned as salesman, selling Klan memberships for $10.00. The local Kleagle kept $4.00, sending $6.00 to the King Kleagle. The King Kleagle kept $1.00, sending $5.00 to the Grand Goblin and so forth, with $2.00 ultimately being deposited in the Imperial Treasury. Each local Kleagle was responsible for a weekly report, sent to the Imperial Kleagle, stating the number of prospective initiates canvassed, the amount of money collected, the towns canvassed that week, and the towns which would be canvassed the following week. The Kleagles also acted as public relations men, explaining the Klan's purpose and doctrines at invitational meetings.
Clifford N. Taylor served as a local Kleagle in Benson, Pierce, and Ramsey counties, North Dakota, during the latter part of 1924. The papers are comprised of two sections: Taylor's business records, arranged by subject, and printed material arranged by title.
The correspondence, arranged chronologically, begins in September 1924 and is mainly between Taylor and "G1 North and South Dakota." (This was probably E. C. Harris, the Imperial Representative in Aberdeen, South Dakota.) The letters, mostly carbons, contain official news and mandates addressed to "All Fieldmen." There are also handwritten copies of letters written by Taylor to the Imperial Representative, asking advice on the recruitment of potential members and questions concerning the reporting procedure. Of particular interest is the discussion concerning the creation of the American Krusaders, a branch of the Ku Klux Klan which admitted foreign-born Protestants. Taylor acted as an "Organizational Representative" for the branch of American Krusaders in Benson, Pierce, and Ramsey counties.
Other subjects of correspondence include the possible formation of a women's branch of the Ku Klux Klan, criticism of the fieldmen for failure to submit weekly reports to the state and national offices, the selection of delegates for an October 26, 1924, Konvention in Aberdeen, South Dakota, expenses, the proper care and marking of Klan robes (including cloth samples), and suggestions for ways to set up meetings for potential members. There are also letters on the offical Klan letterhead from the Imperial Wizard, H. W. Evans, concerning the appointment of a Committee on Constitution and Laws, the misconduct of Klansmen, and the promotion of a high ranking national Klan official.
Eight folders contain weekly reports submitted by Taylor to the Imperial Kleagle for Benson, Pierce, and Ramsey counties for the period September through November 1924. The Kleagle's Weekly Petition Report contained statistics on the number of petitioners who had joined the Klan and paid their initial membership fee. The Organizers Weekly Report contained similar statistics for the American Krusaders. Taylor did not have a great deal of success recruiting new Klan members during this period. The Part Payment Weekly Reports appear to record expenditures. Report Guides for Ramsey County contain information on potential members.
Other material in the Business Records section includes an application and questionnaire for the American Krusaders, bills and receipts, cards belonging to Taylor, a memorandum book containing accounts and lists of names, notes for an unsuccessful invitational meeting held on October 17, 1924, in Devils Lake, North Dakota, and an offical Klan announcement concerning the position of the Klan in politics.
The Printed Material section consists of Ku Klux Klan pamphlets and flyers. "Americans take Heed!" (1920) was originally published in McClure's Magazine as an editorial. "Christian Citizenship" reminds Klansmen of the political convictions of the Klan. "Facts for Patriotic Americans" and "Making American Catholic" contain "facts" about the Catholic Church in the United States. A proclamation, dated 1924, extends an invitation to Klansmen in South Dakota, Iowa, and Nebraska to a Tri-State Konklave and parade to be held in Iowa. Of particular interest is a pamphlet describing the electric cross favored by Ku Klux Klan for use in ceremonies and meetings.
Race discrimination -- North Dakota; Race discrimination -- South Dakota; Secret societies -- North Dakota; Secret societies -- South Dakota; Benson County (N.D.) -- History; North Dakota -- Race relations; Pierce County (N.D.) -- History; Ramsey County (N.D.) -- History; South Dakota -- Race relations; Evans, H. W. (Hiram Wesley); Haynes, E. C.; Taylor, Clifford N.; American Krusaders; Catholic Church -- Social conditions -- North Dakota; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- North Dakota
- Box and Folder List
  - Business Records
    - Application for citizenship in the American Krusaders, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 2-8)
    - Bills and receipts, 1924 Sep-Nov (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cards, 1924, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "(Closing)": typescript, original, [1924] Sep 21 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Invitational meeting: notes, 1924 Oct 17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lists of names, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Memorandum book, 1924 Aug-Nov (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Note, 1924 Dec 4 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Official News and Instructions to be Read in the Klaverns of the Realm: typescript, original (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Questionnaire: American Krusaders, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Weekly reports
    - Kleagle's weekly petition reports
      - Benson County, North Dakota, 1924 Nov (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Pierce County, North Dakota, 1924 Nov (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Ramsey County, North Dakota, 1924 Sep-Nov (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Organizer's weekly petiton reports
      - Benson County, North Dakota, 1924 Nov (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Ramsey County, North Dakota, 1924 Nov (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Part payment weekly report
      - Benson County, North Dakota, 1924 Nov (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Pierce County, North Dakota, 1924 Nov (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Ramsey County, North Dakota, 1924 Nov (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Report guides: Ramsey County, North Dakota, 1924 Oct 18 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Printed material
    - "Americans, take Heed!": pamphlet, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "Christian Citizenship": pamphlet, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "Facts for Patriotic Americans": pamphlet, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "Genuine K. K. K. Flour": clipping, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - "Making America Catholic...": pamphlet, 1923 Jul (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - "The Old Rugged Cross": pamphlet, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "Proclamation. Realm of Iowa. A Monster Tri State Konklave and Parade", 1924 Oct 11 (Box 1, Folder 33)